<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Storage | atomic-penguin's personal webpage.]]></title>
  <link href="http://atomic-penguin.github.com/blog/categories/storage/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://atomic-penguin.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-08-27T16:08:56-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://atomic-penguin.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Eric G. Wolfe]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Red Hat Enterprise Linux 5.x iSCSI and Device Mapper Multipath HOWTO]]></title>
    <link href="http://atomic-penguin.github.com/blog/2010/11/29/Red-Hat-Enterprise-Linux-5.x-iSCSI-and-device-mapper-multipath-HOWTO/"/>
    <updated>2010-11-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://atomic-penguin.github.com/blog/2010/11/29/Red-Hat-Enterprise-Linux-5.x-iSCSI-and-device-mapper-multipath-HOWTO</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Abstract</h2>

<p><img src="/images/muwam.png" alt="Marshall University Systems Infrastructure Team" /></p>

<p>This document outlines in a detailed step-by-step fashion,
how to properly configure iSCSI initiator, and multi-path I/O
software on Red Hat Enterprise Linux version 5.</p>

<pre><code>Copyright © 2010, Marshall University Systems Infrastructure Team
Author: Eric G. Wolfe 
Contributor: Jaymz Mynes 
Editor: Tim Calvert 

Marshall University 
400 Hal Greer Blvd. 
Huntington, WV 25755 

This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share 
Alike 3.0 United States License. To view a copy of this license, 
visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/us/ 
or send a letter to Creative Commons, 171 Second Street, Suite 
300, San Francisco, California, 94105, USA. 

The block M logo is a trademark of Marshall University. All other 
trademarks are owned by their respective owners. 
</code></pre>

<!-- more -->


<h2>I. Introduction</h2>

<p>The following configuration was documented and tested on a Dell
Poweredge R710, with RedHat Enterprise Linux 5.0 x64. The R710
server has 4 Broadcom NeteXtreme II BCM5709 Gigabit Network
Interface Cards (NIC), and is connected by Ethernet to an EqualLogic
PS6000 storage array.</p>

<p>This step-by-step guide is directly applicable to these software
and hardware components. However, much of the software configuration
would remain the same for any Linux distribution
on either X86 or AMD64
based hardware. The most dynamic variable in any case will be
specific storage solutions. Consider any factors that your
storage vendor may support, or recommend, before proceeding.</p>

<h3>II. Hardware Preparation</h3>

<p>Appropriate hardware preparation is beyond the scope of this
document. See vendor documentation for connecting Ethernet
cables to the storage array, and appropriate configuration
of the storage array. According to Dell EqualLogic (2008) some
recommended guidelines are as follows:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Do...</p></li>
<li><p>Do NOT...</p></li>
</ul>


<p>See <em>PS Series Array Network Performance Guidelines</em>, or relevant
storage vendor's documentation for more information.</p>

<p>III. Manual Installation</p>

<p>The following section outlines manual installation and configuration
of Device Mapper Multipath and Open-iSCSI initiator on Red Hat
Enterprise Linux version 5.x. If this is your first time installing
and configuring Device Mapper Multipath, or Open-iSCSI software,
then this is the recommended method of installation and configuration.
It is possible to automate a portion of this installation and
configuration with Red Hat's Kickstart, or configuration management
engines such as Puppet. However, that is beyond the scope of this
document.</p>

<p>The methods outlined in this guide apply directly to Red Hat Enterprise
Linux, {text:change} {text:change-start} though {text:change-end}
a major portion of the configuration items are generic and could
be applied to other Linux distributions. The author of this HOWTO
assumes these steps will, for the most part, remain constant
for subsequent versions of Red Hat Enterprise Linux.</p>

<h2>1. Package Installation</h2>

<p>After performing a base install of Red Hat Enterprise v5, make
sure to upgrade the system to the latest patch-level.</p>

<blockquote><p>Change this line in <em>/etc/yum.conf</em> as illustrated below.</p></blockquote>

<p>exclude=kernel*</p>

<blockquote><p>Comment out the exclude options, so the kernel may be upgraded.</p></blockquote>

<p>exclude=#kernel*</p>

<blockquote><p>Run the following to upgrade to the latest patch-level.</p></blockquote>

<p>yum -y upgrade</p>

<blockquote><p>Run the following to install needed software.</p></blockquote>

<p>{text:change-start} yum -y install iscsi-initiator-utils
device-mapper-multipath {text:change-end}</p>

<p>Dell Equallogic (2009) recommends using RHEL 5.4 (version 5
update 4) or newer for best performance and interoperability
with PS Series storage arrays. Ensure the following requirements
are met before proceeding.</p>

<blockquote><p>Run the following to check for minimum package versions.</p></blockquote>

<p>rpm -qa iscsi-initiator-utils device-mapper-multipath</p>

<p>device-mapper-multipath-<version>-<patch-level>.el5</p>

<p>iscsi-initiator-utils-<version>-<patch-level>.el5</p>

<blockquote></blockquote>

<ul>
<li><p>Minimum package version for PS Series arrays</p></li>
<li><p>Minimum package version for GbE NICs</p></li>
<li><p>With SELinux enabled, you may not be able to login to iSCSI targets.
You may have to create a policy for iSCSI traffic, or disable
{text:change} {text:change-start} SELinux {text:change-end}
.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>After updating the kernel, you will need to reboot the system,
before proceeding. This would be a good time to pick an appropriate
I/O scheduler. Available I/O schedulers, and the kernel option
to select them, are as follows.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Completely Fair Queueing – elevator=cfq</p></li>
<li><p>Deadline – {text:change-start} <strong>elevator=deadline</strong>
{text:change-end}</p></li>
<li><p>NOOP – {text:change-start} <strong>elevator=noop</strong> {text:change-end}</p></li>
<li><p>Anticipatory – elevator=as</p></li>
</ul>


<p>According to a citation in Dell Equallogic (2009), the Open-iSCSI
group reports that sometimes the NOOP scheduler works best for
iSCSI server environments. However, if this server will be used
as an Oracle database or application server, it is standard best
practice to use the Deadline scheduler for optimal performance.</p>

<blockquote><p>Run the following command to enable the NOOP scheduler, before
rebooting.</p></blockquote>

<p>sed -e 's!/vmlinuz.*!&amp; elevator=noop!g' -i /boot/grub/menu.lst</p>

<blockquote><p>If you are provisioning an Oracle server, then run the following
to select Deadline.</p></blockquote>

<p>sed -e 's!/vmlinuz.*!&amp; elevator=deadline!g' -i /boot/grub/menu.lst</p>

<p>Finally, reboot the server after upgrading the system and kernel.
Do this before proceeding with the configuration steps that
follow {text:change} {text:change} so the proper I/O scheduler
will be active and the newer kernel will be available. You may
also want to go back and uncomment the <em>exclude=#kernel*</em> line
in <em>/etc/yum.conf</em>, at your own discretion.</p>

<p>IV. Configuring Open-iSCSI</p>

<h3>1. Configuring the NIC cards for iSCSI use</h3>

<p>In the following example, it is assumed you will be using the third
(eth2) and fourth (eth3) Network Interface Cards in the system
for iSCSI traffic. If this is not the case, then adjust the configuration
for different NICs as necessary.</p>

<p>Add the following bold lines to each of the <em>ifcfg-ethX</em> scripts
for each iSCSI NIC. Ensure that <em>IPADDR</em>, and <em>NETMASK</em> are correctly
set for your iSCSI subnet. Make sure <em>ONBOOT</em> is set to <em>yes</em>.
This is set so that each interface will be automatically initialized
when the system is booted. The <em>MTU</em> variable should be set to
<em>9000</em>, for each iSCSI NIC, this MTU setting will enable jumbo
frames.</p>

<p><em>/etc/sysconfig/</em> {text:change} {text:change-start} <em>network-scripts</em>
{text:change-end} <em>/ifcfg-eth2</em></p>

<h1>Broadcom Corporation NetXtreme II BCM5709 Gigabit Ethernet</h1>

<p>DEVICE=eth2</p>

<p>HWADDR=00:11:22:33:44:aa</p>

<p>ONBOOT=yes</p>

<p>BOOTPROTO=none</p>

<p>NETMASK=255.255.255.0</p>

<p>IPADDR=10.1.2.3</p>

<p>TYPE=Ethernet</p>

<p>MTU=9000</p>

<p><em>/etc/sysconfig/network</em> {text:change} {text:change-start}
<em>-scripts</em> {text:change-end} <em>/ifcfg-eth3</em></p>

<h1>Broadcom Corporation NetXtreme II BCM5709 Gigabit Ethernet</h1>

<p>DEVICE=eth3</p>

<p>HWADDR=00:11:22:33:44:bb</p>

<p>ONBOOT=yes</p>

<p>BOOTPROTO=none</p>

<p>NETMASK=255.255.255.0</p>

<p>IPADDR=10.1.2.4</p>

<p>TYPE=Ethernet</p>

<p>MTU=9000</p>

<p>Dell EqualLogic (2009) recommends enabling Flow Control, and
disabling Auto Negotiation on each iSCSI NIC. For these settings
to be automatically applied upon each boot, add the following
code, in boldface, to the <em>/etc/rc.local</em> file.</p>

<p>/etc/rc.local</p>

<h1>iSCSI Interface Settings for Equallogic</h1>

<p>ISCSI_IF="eth2 eth3"</p>

<p>ETHTOOL_OPTS="autoneg off rx on tx on"</p>

<p>ETHTOOL=<code>which ethtool</code></p>

<p>for i in $ISCSI_IF;</p>

<p>do</p>

<p>echo "$ETHTOOL -A $i $ETHTOOL_OPTS"</p>

<p>$ETHTOOL -A $ISCSI_IF $ETHTOOL_OPTS</p>

<p>done</p>

<p>1.1. Configuring Open-iSCSI initiator utilities</p>

<p>You need to tune a few lines in the <em>/etc/iscsi/iscid.conf</em> file,
per vendor recommendations. You can grep out blank and comment
lines in this file for quick inspection. The lines we are most
concerned {text:change-start} about {text:change-end} will
appear in bold. Values set per specific vendor recommendations
are highlighted in red.</p>

<h4>1.1.1. Notes about iscsid.conf configuration</h4>

<p>As I understand it, the configuration item, <em>node.session.timeo.replacement_timeout</em>
is for specifying the length of time, in seconds, {text:change-start}
after {text:change-end} which the iSCSI layer will fail back
to the Device Mapper Multipath application layer. By default,
this is 120 seconds, or 2 minutes. According to Red Hat (2008),
it is preferable to pass the path failure quickly from the SCSI
layer to your Multipath software, which would be necessary for
quick fail-over. With the default configuration, two minutes
of I/O would be queued before failing the path. If you are familiar
with Fiber Channel path fail-over, it tends to be instantaneous.
Most people configuring iSCSI fail-over certainly don't want
a failed path to be retried for two whole minutes. Using the default
configuration with a production database server could lead
to massive amounts of I/O being queued {text:change} {text:change-start}
i {text:change-end} nstead of the expected behavior of failing
over to another working path quickly. Changing this value to
15 {text:change} {text:change} will {text:change-start}
allow the path to failover {text:change-end} {text:change}
much {text:change} {text:change-start} more quickly {text:change-end}
.</p>

<p>According to Dell (2010), if the Broadcom bnx2i interface fails
to login to an Equallogic iSCSI storage volume, the <em>node.session.initial_login_retry_max</em>
should be changed from the default value of <em>8</em> to <em>12</em> {text:change-end}
{text:change} {text:change-start} .</p>

<p>According to Dell Equallogic (2009) the options <em>node.session.cmds_max</em>,
and <em>node.session.queue_depth</em> should be changed for Equallogic
arrays. The recommendation for <em>node.session.cmds_max</em> is
to change the value from <em>128</em> {text:change-end} {text:change}
{text:change-start} _ to <strong>1024</strong>. <em>The recommendation for
</em>node.session.queue_depth<em> is to change the value from </em>32<em>
{text:change-end} {text:change} {text:change} {text:change-start}
to </em>128_.</p>

<p>Finally, according to the in-line comments in the default iscsid.conf,
and Dell (2010) Equallogic arrays should have <em>node.session.isci.FastAbort</em>
set to <em>No</em>. If using software such as iSCSI Enterprise Target
(IET), instead of an Equallogic Array, leave the <em>FastAbort</em>
value set to the default, which is <em>Yes</em>. {text:change-end}</p>

<p>1.1.2. iscsid.conf {text:change}</p>

<p>egrep -v “<sup>(#|$)”</sup> /etc/iscsi/iscid.conf</p>

<p>node.startup = automatic</p>

<p><strong>node.session.timeo.replacement_timeout = </strong><strong>15</strong>**</p>

<h1>default 120; RedHat recommended**</h1>

<p>node.conn[0].timeo.login_timeout = 15</p>

<p>node.conn[0].timeo.logout_timeout = 15</p>

<p>node.conn[0].timeo.noop_out_interval = 5</p>

<p>node.conn[0].timeo.noop_out_timeout = 5</p>

<p>node.session.err_timeo.abort_timeout = 15</p>

<p>node.session.err_timeo.lu_reset_timeout = 20</p>

<p><strong>node.session.initial_login_retry_max = </strong><strong>12</strong><strong> # default
8; Dell recommended</strong></p>

<p><strong>node.session.cmds_max = </strong><strong>1024</strong><strong> # default 128; Equallogic
recommended</strong></p>

<p><strong>node.session.queue_depth = </strong><strong>128</strong><strong> # default 32; Equallogic
recommended</strong></p>

<p>node.session.iscsi.InitialR2T = No</p>

<p>node.session.iscsi.ImmediateData = Yes</p>

<p>node.session.iscsi.FirstBurstLength = 262144</p>

<p>node.session.iscsi.MaxBurstLength = 16776192</p>

<p>node.conn[0].iscsi.MaxRecvDataSegmentLength = 262144</p>

<p>discovery.sendtargets.iscsi.MaxRecvDataSegmentLength
= 32768</p>

<p>node.conn[0].iscsi.HeaderDigest = None</p>

<p><strong>node.session.iscsi.FastAbort = </strong><strong>No</strong><strong> # default Yes;
Dell / Open-iSCSI recommended</strong></p>

<h1>IV. Targeting and Logging in with iscsiadm</h1>

<h2>1. Create iSCSI interfaces</h2>

<p>The iSCSI interfaces are separate pseudo-devices used by Open-iSCSI.
From Open-iSCSI's point-of-view, these are not the same as physical
Ethernet devices. What you'll need to do is bind {text:change-start}
each of {text:change-end} your ethX devices to an iSCSI interface.
Technically speaking, you could call your iSCSI interfaces
{text:change} {text:change} eth2 and eth3, and bind them to
the corresponding physical devices in the /dev folder. To avoid
any confusion about physical NICs and iSCSI interfaces, it {text:change-start}
’ {text:change-end} s {text:change} recommended to give the
interfaces different names like iface0 and iface1.</p>

<p>{text:change} {text:change-start} You can {text:change-end}
create your iSCSI interfaces with the following commands.</p>

<p>iscsiadm -m iface -I iface0 -o new</p>

<p>iscsiadm -m iface -I iface1 -o new</p>

<p>Second, let {text:change-start} ’ {text:change-end} s {text:change}
take a look at the iSCSI interface properties for one of our new
interfaces. This will come in handy to view the currently active
configuration {text:change} {text:change} in cases where
you need to troubleshoot {text:change} .</p>

<p>{text:change-start} {text:change-end} {text:change-start}
This is how you can look at the iSCSI interface properties for
one of the new interfaces. {text:change-end} {text:change-start}
Being able to view the currently active configuration can come
in handy in cases where you need to troubleshoot. {text:change-end}
{text:change-start} {text:change-end}</p>

<p>iscsiadm -m iface -I iface0</p>

<p>{text:soft-page-break} # BEGIN RECORD 2.0-871</p>

<p>iface.iscsi_ifacename = iface0</p>

<p>iface.net_ifacename = <empty></p>

<p>iface.ipaddress = <empty></p>

<p>iface.hwaddress = <empty></p>

<p>iface.transport_name = tcp</p>

<p>iface.initiatorname = <empty></p>

<h1>END RECORD</h1>

<h2>2. Bind iSCSI interfaces</h2>

<p>Now that we have iSCSI interfaces, we need to bind them to a physical
Ethernet device. You can use either a device name {text:change}
{text:change} or MAC address. Open-iSCSI won't even let you
bind the interfaces with both {text:change} a device name {text:change}
{text:change} and MAC address.</p>

<p>Binding by physical device name</p>

<p>iscsiadm -m iface {text:change-start} -o update {text:change-end}
-I iface0 -n iface.net_ifacename -v eth2</p>

<p>iscsiadm -m iface {text:change-start} -o update {text:change-end}
-I iface1 -n iface.net_ifacename -v eth3</p>

<p>Binding by MAC address</p>

<p>iscsiadm -m iface {text:change-start} -o update {text:change-end}
-I iface0 -n iface.hwaddress -v 00:aa:bb:cc:dd:ee</p>

<p>iscsiadm -m iface {text:change-start} -o update {text:change-end}
-I iface1 -n iface.hwaddress -v 00:aa:bb:cc:dd:ff</p>

<p>An important note about alternate transport drivers for iSCSI
offload: By default, your new iSCSI interfaces will use TCP as
the iSCSI transport. There are other offload transport drivers
available to use, such as <strong>bnx2i</strong>, <strong>iser</strong>, and <strong>cxgb3i</strong>.
According to the iscsiadm manual page and personal conversation
with a Dell storage engineer, these are experimental drivers
which are not supported or considered stable.</p>

<h3>2.1. Updating iSCSI interfaces</h3>

<p>If you bind an interface by MAC address, and have a hardware replacement
which changes the MAC address. Then the iSCSI interface bindings
will need {text:change-start} to be {text:change-end} updated
{text:change} {text:change} to reflect such system changes.
You can do this with {text:change} {text:change-start} an {text:change-end}
update command {text:change} {text:change} {text:change-start}
: {text:change-end}</p>

<p>iscsiadm -m iface -o update -I iface0 -n iface.hwaddress -v 00:aa:bb:cc:dd:11</p>

<p>iscsiadm -m iface -o update -I iface1 -n iface.hwaddress -v 00:aa:bb:cc:dd:33</p>

<h2>3. Connecting to the iSCSI array</h2>

<p>The file <em>/etc/iscsi/initiatorname.iscsi</em> should contain
an initiator name for your iSCSI client host. You need to include
this initiator name on your iSCSI array's configuration for
this specific iSCSI client host.</p>

<p>If you haven't yet started the iSCSI daemon, run the following
command before we commence with discovering targets.</p>

<p>{text:soft-page-break}</p>

<p>service iscsid start</p>

<h3>3.1 Discovering targets</h3>

<p>Once the iscsid service is running {text:change} {text:change}
and the client's initiator name is configured on the iSCSI array
{text:change} {text:change} {text:change-start} , {text:change-end}
then you may proceed with the following command to discover available
targets. Assuming our iSCSI array had an IP address of 10.1.2.10,
the following command would return the available targets.</p>

<p>iscsiadm -m discovery -t st -p 10.1.2.10:3260</p>

<p>10.1.2.10:3260,1 iqn.2001-05.com.equallogic:0-8a0906-7008ec504-23d000000204bad0-hostname-vol0</p>

<p>10.1.2.10:3260,1 iqn.2001-05.com.equallogic:0-8a0906-7008ec504-23d000000204bad0-hostname-vol0</p>

<h3>3.2. Login to target</h3>

<p>We're finally ready to login to our target {text:change} {text:change}
{text:change-start} . {text:change-end} {text:change} {text:change-start}
T {text:change-end} o log in to all targets, use the following
command. This should return successful {text:change} {text:change}
if everything is working correctly.</p>

<p>iscsiadm -m node -l</p>

<p>Individual targets can be logged into {text:change} {text:change}
by specifying a whole target name.</p>

<p><strong>iscsiadm -m node -T </strong><strong><em>iqn.2001-05.com.equallogic:0-8a0906-7008ec504-23d000000204bad0-hostname-vol0
-l -p 10.1.2.10:3260</em></strong></p>

<h3>3.3. Logoff a target</h3>

<p>Logging off is basically the same as logging into a target, except
you use <em>-u</em> {text:change} {text:change} instead of <em>-l.</em></p>

<p>iscsiadm -m node -u</p>

<h3></h3>

<p>3.4. Session status</p>

<p>The session command can be used to print the basic status {text:change}
{text:change} or more verbose output for debugging and troubleshooting.</p>

<p>Basic command {text:change} {text:change-start} : {text:change-end}</p>

<p>iscsiadm -m session</p>

<p>tcp: [10] 10.1.2.10:3260,1 iqn.2001-05.com.equallogic:0-8a0906-7008ec504-23d000000204bad0-hostname-vol0</p>

<p>tcp: [9] 10.1.2.10:3260,1 iqn.2001-05.com.equallogic:0-8a0906-7008ec504-23d000000204bad0-hostname-vol0</p>

<p>Troubleshooting information with -P (print) flag {text:change}
{text:change} and verbosity level 0-3 {text:change} {text:change-start}
: {text:change-end}</p>

<p>iscsiadm -m session -P3</p>

<p>iSCSI Transport Class version 2.0-871</p>

<p>version 2.0-871</p>

<p>Target: iqn.2001-05.com.equallogic:0-8a0906-7008ec504-23d000000204bad0-hostname-vol0</p>

<p>Current Portal: 10.1.2.25:3260,1</p>

<p>Persistent Portal: 10.1.2.10:3260,1</p>

<hr />

<p>Interface:</p>

<hr />

<p>Iface Name: iface0</p>

<p>Iface Transport: tcp</p>

<p>Iface Initiatorname: iqn.1994-05.com.redhat:13c39f80866f</p>

<p>Iface IPaddress: 10.1.2.3</p>

<p>Iface HWaddress: <empty></p>

<p>Iface Netdev: eth2</p>

<p>SID: 10</p>

<p>iSCSI Connection State: LOGGED IN</p>

<p>iSCSI Session State: LOGGED_IN</p>

<p>Internal iscsid Session State: NO CHANGE</p>

<hr />

<p>Negotiated iSCSI params:</p>

<hr />

<p>HeaderDigest: None</p>

<p>DataDigest: None</p>

<p>MaxRecvDataSegmentLength: 262144</p>

<p>MaxXmitDataSegmentLength: 65536</p>

<p>FirstBurstLength: 65536</p>

<p>MaxBurstLength: 262144</p>

<p>ImmediateData: Yes</p>

<p>InitialR2T: No</p>

<p>MaxOutstandingR2T: 1</p>

<hr />

<p>Attached SCSI devices:</p>

<hr />

<p>Host Number: 27 State: running</p>

<p>scsi27 Channel 00 Id 0 Lun: 0</p>

<p>Attached scsi disk sdc State: running</p>

<p>V. Configuring Device Mapper Multipath</p>

<h2>1. Notes about the Device Mapper Multipath example</h2>

<p>The final major step is to configure Device Mapper Multipath
{text:change} {text:change} using the configuration file
<em>/etc/multipath.conf</em>. By default there will be a <em>devnode
“*”</em> line in the <em>blacklist</em> section, thereby disabling Multipath
for all devices in the system. If you want to assign persistently
bound names to iSCSI devices, {text:change} be sure to set <em>user_friendly_names</em>
to yes, as seen in the example on the following page. If you do not
use friendly names with Device Mapper, you'll end up with device
names such as <em>/dev/mapper/__36090afffffffffffffffffffffffffff</em>.
When using friendly names, you'll need to specify an <em>alias</em>
line in the <em>multipaths</em> section after Open-iSCSI is configured
and working correctly with your iSCSI target {text:change}
{text:change} or array.</p>

<p>You will want to blacklist any local devices that do not have multiple
paths to be managed {text:change} {text:change} in the <em>blacklist</em>
section. It is recommended to blacklist the local SCSI disks
by World Wide Identifier (WWID). The WWID is a unique identifier
for any block device {text:change} {text:change} and may be
retrieved with the command <em>scsi_id -g -u -s /block/sdX</em>, where
X is the letter identifier of the local SCSI disk. It cannot hurt
to also blacklist local devices by physical device name with
a <em>devnode</em> line and a Perl-compatible regular expression string.
The reason for blacklisting a second time with a regular expression
is in case the <em>scsi_id</em> program fails to read the WWID from sector
zero of a local device. See the blacklist section in the configuration
example. The WWID line {text:change} {text:change} and _devnode
“<sup>sd[a]$”_</sup> line both serve as a blacklist for device sda.</p>

<p>Once you have discovered targets {text:change} {text:change}
and logged in to the iSCSI array, you can use the '<em>iscsiadm -m
session -P3'</em> command to find the physical device names of your
iSCSI volumes. Then you can use {text:change} {text:change}
the '<em>scsi_id -g -u -s /block/sdX'</em> command to find the WWID of
your iSCSI volumes. Once you have the WWIDs of your iSCSI volumes,
you can configure friendly name aliases in the <em>multipaths</em>
section, as seen {text:change-start} in the example {text:change-end}
on the next page {text:change} .</p>

<p>The device section in the configuration example is pertinent
to an Equallogic PS Series array. The lines in boldface type are
of particular importance, and are the recommended defaults
for Equallogic devices. You can override the parameters on a
per-volume basis in the <em>multipaths</em> section.</p>

<p>{text:change-start} For best performance, {text:change-end}
{text:change} {text:change-start} t {text:change-end} he
value for <em>rr_min_io</em> should {text:change} {text:change-start}
be {text:change-end} in the range of {text:change-start} <em>10-20</em>
{text:change-end} for database environments. {text:change-start}
For {text:change-end} {text:change} {text:change-start}
m {text:change-end} ore sequential loads {text:change-start}
, {text:change-end} which may be seen on file servers, {text:change}
{text:change-start} performance might be better if {text:change-end}
<em>rr_min_io</em> {text:change} is set in the range {text:change-start}
<em>100-512</em> {text:change-end} . Any <em>rr_min_io</em> value over {text:change-start}
<em>200</em> {text:change-end} will require max commands and queue
depths parameters in <em>iscsid.conf</em> to be increased.</p>

<p>1.1. multipath.conf</p>

<p>defaults {</p>

<p>user_friendly_names yes</p>

<p>}</p>

<p>blacklist {</p>

<p>wwid 360924fffffffffffffffffffffffffff</p>

<p>devnode "<sup>sd[a]$"</sup></p>

<p>devnode "<sup>(ram|raw|loop|fd|md|dm-|sr|scd|st)[0-9]*"</sup></p>

<p>devnode "<sup>hd[a-z][[0-9]*]"</sup></p>

<p>devnode "<sup>cciss!c[0-9]d[0-9]<em>[p[0-9]</em>]"</sup></p>

<p>}</p>

<p>devices {</p>

<p>device {</p>

<p><strong>vendor "EQLOGIC"</strong></p>

<p><strong>product "100E-00"</strong></p>

<p>path_grouping_policy multibus</p>

<p>getuid_callout "/sbin/scsi_id -g -u -s /block/%n" {text:change}</p>

<p>{text:change-start} <strong>no_path_retry </strong> {text:change-end}
{text:change} {text:change} {text:change-start} {text:change-start}
<strong>queue</strong> {text:change-end} {text:change-end}</p>

<p>path_checker readsector0</p>

<p>failback immediate</p>

<p>path_selector "round-robin 0"</p>

<p><strong>rr_min_io 10</strong></p>

<p>rr_weight priorities</p>

<p>}</p>

<p>}</p>

<p>multipaths {</p>

<p>multipath {</p>

<p>wwid 36090afffffffffffffffffffffffffff</p>

<p>alias u02</p>

<p>}</p>

<p>}</p>

<h2>1.2. Start and test Device Mapper Multipath</h2>

<p>Device Mapper Multipath can be started with the following command
{text:change} {text:change} once it has been configured.</p>

<p>service multipathd start</p>

<p>You can list the Multipath topology with the following command
to verify everything is working correctly.</p>

<p>multipath -ll -v2</p>

<p>u02 (36090a04850ec0870d0ba04020000d023) dm-0 EQLOGIC,100E-00</p>

<p>[size=100G][features=0][hwhandler=0][rw]</p>

<p>_ round-robin 0 [prio=2][active]</p>

<p>_ 10:0:0:0 sdb 8:16 [active][ready]</p>

<p>_ 11:0:0:0 sdc 8:32 [active][ready]</p>

<h2>{text:soft-page-break} 1.3. Reload udev to test friendly alias names</h2>

<p>Once Multipath has been verified to be working correctly, {text:change}
you may need to run the following <em>udev</em> command to create {text:change-start}
devices with {text:change-end} friendly name {text:change-start}
s {text:change-end} {text:change} . This only applies if you
have chosen to use persistent Multipath binding by defining
<em>alias</em> lines in the <em>multipaths</em> section of <em>multipath.conf</em>.
Reloading udev {text:change} {text:change} will automagically
{text:change} create your aliased devices in the <em>/dev/mapper</em>
folder.</p>

<p>Reload udev command {text:change} {text:change} {text:change-start}
: {text:change-end}</p>

<p>udevcontrol reload_rules</p>

<p>You may proceed to <em>fdisk</em> {text:change} {text:change} and
format the aliased device, just as you would any other SCSI disk
device appearing in the /dev directory.</p>

<h1>VI. Final steps</h1>

<h2>1. Set services to start automatically.</h2>

<p>Once you have everything up and running, with regards to Open-iSCSI
and Device Mapper Multipath, {text:change} run the following
commands to ensure services get started automatically during
server boot {text:change-start} {text:change-end} up {text:change}
.</p>

<p>Set the iscsid daemon to start automatically {text:change}
{text:change} {text:change-start} : {text:change-end}</p>

<p>chkconfig iscsid on</p>

<p>Set the iscsi service to log in to targets automatically {text:change}
{text:change} {text:change-start} : {text:change-end}</p>

<p>chkconfig iscsi on</p>

<p>Set the multipathd daemon to start automatically {text:change}
{text:change} {text:change-start} : {text:change-end}</p>

<p>chkconfig multipathd on</p>

<p>Edit <em>/etc/fstab</em>, and add a line with the <strong>netdev_ keyword
for all your volumes to be mounted. Using the </strong>netdev_ keyword
ensures this device will not be mounted before the networking
subsystem has started. {text:change-start}</p>

<p>We've observe {text:change-end} {text:change-start} d Open-iSCSI
failing both paths temporarily while updating firmware on the
group node. {text:change-end} {text:change-start} This could
result in a machine remounting a filesystem in read-only mode
upon error unless an '<em>errors=continue</em>' option is added to
/etc/fstab. {text:change-end}</p>

<p>LABEL=/ {text:change} / {text:change} ext3 defaults 1 1</p>

<p>LABEL=/u01 {text:change} /u01 {text:change} ext3 defaults
1 2</p>

<p>/dev/mapper/u02p1 {text:change} /u02 {text:change} {text:change}
ext3 _netdev,defaults {text:change-start} ,errors=continue
{text:change-end} 0 0</p>

<p>tmpfs {text:change} /dev/shm {text:change} tmpfs defaults
0 0</p>

<p>devpts {text:change} /dev/pts {text:change} devpts gid=5,mode=620
0 0</p>

<p>sysfs {text:change} /sys {text:change} sysfs defaults 0 0</p>

<p>proc {text:change} /proc {text:change} {text:change} proc
defaults 0 0</p>

<p>LABEL=SWAP-sda5 {text:change} swap {text:change} swap defaults
0 0</p>

<h2>2. Final testing</h2>

<h3>2.1. Reboot</h3>

<p>Reboot your server, and make sure everything comes up. The iscsi
initialization script should log the server in to the iSCSI targets.
Multipath should be started, and {text:change-start} it should
{text:change-end} see both of its paths to the iSCSI array. If
everything is working correctly, the <em>fstab</em> entry should automatically
mount any iSCSI volumes.</p>

<h3>2.2. Test your Multipath software</h3>

<p>The easiest way to test your Multipath software is to take down
one of the Ethernet devices manually. {text:change-start}
To do this, {text:change-end} {text:change} {text:change-start}
r {text:change-end} un the following command.</p>

<p>ifdown eth3</p>

<p>After about 15 seconds you should see something like this in the
messages log.</p>

<p>kernel: device-mapper: multipath: Failing path X:XX</p>

<p>multipathd: <alias>: remaining active paths: 1</p>

<p>Then, bring the device back up manually {text:change} {text:change}
{text:change-start} : {text:change-end}</p>

<p>ifup eth3</p>

<p>Again, after about 15 seconds you should see something like this
in the messages log.</p>

<p>multipathd: X:XX: reinstated</p>

<p>multipathd: <alias>: remaining active paths: 2</p>

<p>Repeat this test for every other NIC being used for iSCSI {text:change}
{text:change} and make sure every iSCSI Network Interface fails-over
from faulty paths, and reinstate {text:change} all active iSCSI
paths {text:change} {text:change} gracefully.</p>

<p>References and recommended reading</p>

<p>Aizman, Alex, and Dmitry Yusupov. 2007. Open-iSCSI – RFC3720
architecture and implementation. <em>Open-iSCSI project</em>. <a href="http://www.open-iscsi.org/index.html#docs">http://www.open-iscsi.org/index.html#docs</a>.</p>

<blockquote><p>Anon. Device-mapper Resource Page. <em>Device-Mapper-Multipath
Project</em>. <a href="http://sources.redhat.com/dm/">http://sources.redhat.com/dm/</a>.</p>

<p>Dell EqualLogic, Inc. 2008. <em>PS Series Array Network Performance
Guidelines</em>. 3rd ed. Nashua, NH: Dell, Inc, June. <a href="http://www.equallogic.com/uploadedfiles/Resources/Tech_Reports/tr-network-guidelines-TR1017.pdf">http://www.equallogic.com/uploadedfiles/Resources/Tech_Reports/tr-network-guidelines-TR1017.pdf</a>.</p>

<p>———. 2009. <em>Red Hat Linux v5.x Software iSCSI Initiator Configuration,
MPIO and tuning Guide</em>. Nashua, NH: Dell, Inc, December. <a href="http://www.equallogic.com/resourcecenter/assetview.aspx?id=8727">http://www.equallogic.com/resourcecenter/assetview.aspx?id=8727</a>.</p>

<p>Red Hat, Inc. 2007. How do I configure the iscsi-initiator in
Red Hat Enterprise Linux 5? <em>Red Hat Knowledgebase</em>. June 25.
<a href="http://access.redhat.com/kb/docs/DOC-6388">https://access.redhat.com/kb/docs/DOC-6388</a>.</p>

<p>———. 2008. How can I improve the failover time of a faulty path
when using device-mapper-multipath over iSCSI? <em>Red Hat Knowledgebase</em>.
October 1. <a href="https://access.redhat.com/kb/docs/DOC-2877">https://access.redhat.com/kb/docs/DOC-2877</a>.</p>

<p>———. 2010a. <em>DM Multipath</em>. <a href="http://www.redhat.com/docs/en-US/Red_Hat_Enterprise_Linux/5.5/html/DM_Multipath/index.html">http://www.redhat.com/docs/en-US/Red_Hat_Enterprise_Linux/5.5/html/DM_Multipath/index.html</a>.</p>

<p>———. 2010b. Kickstart Installations. In <em>Installing Red Hat
Enterprise Linux 5 for all architectures</em>, Chap. 31. Research
Triangle Park, NC: Red Hat, Inc. <a href="http://www.redhat.com/docs/en-US/Red_Hat_Enterprise_Linux/5.5/html/Installation_Guide/index.html">http://www.redhat.com/docs/en-US/Red_Hat_Enterprise_Linux/5.5/html/Installation_Guide/index.html</a>.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
