<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: 2 Cent Tip | atomic-penguin's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://atomic-penguin.github.com/blog/categories/2-cent-tip/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://atomic-penguin.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-29T13:55:39-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://atomic-penguin.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Eric G. Wolfe]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2 Cent Linux Tip Using Find and Tar for a Selective Backup]]></title>
    <link href="http://atomic-penguin.github.com/blog/2011/07/11/2-cent-linux-tip-using-find-and-tar-for-a-selective-backup/"/>
    <updated>2011-07-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://atomic-penguin.github.com/blog/2011/07/11/2-cent-linux-tip-using-find-and-tar-for-a-selective-backup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So I\&rsquo;m blowing away, and re-installing, my Steam Bottle on <a href="http://codeweavers.com">Codeweaver\&rsquo;s</a> Crossover games.  I was hoping to get some in-game overlay support for the Community/Friends features of Steam.  I really really want to hang on to Team Fortress/Left 4 Dead settings though.</p>

<p>Using the <code>find</code> command we can solve this problem fairly easy.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>So the basic requirements in this scenario boil down to finding all the config files under the <code>~/.cxgames</code> tree. I have an <code>~/etc</code> directory to keep a backup of important things such as settings and handy scripts. I will copy my tar file to the <code>~/etc</code> directory so I can find it easily later. However, I don&rsquo;t want every <code>*.cfg</code> file under my Steam bottle, just the ones for those specific games (Team Fortress and Left 4 Dead). When I run the following command, I\&rsquo;ll discover those games have a common top-level directory, <em>~/.cxgames/Steam/drive_c/Program Files/Steam/steamapps</em>.</p>

<p><div>
  <pre><code class='bash'>&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;find ~/.cxgames -name &quot;*.cfg&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</code></pre>
</div>
</p>

<p>When I run the following command, however, I&rsquo;ll get an error due to spaces in the directory/filename structure.  Note the backslash in &ldquo;Program Files&rdquo; is an escaped space for the shell to properly interpret this.</p>

<p><div>
  <pre><code class='bash'>&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;find .cxgames/Steam/drive_c/Program\ Files/Steam/steamapps/ | xargs tar -rf ~/etc/steam-settings.tar
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</code></pre>
</div>
</p>

<p>The find command has a switch <code>-print0</code> to deal with this, and <code>xargs</code> will process this find output format with the <code>-0</code> flag.  The <code>-print0</code> and <code>-0</code> flags tell these system utilities to print or use null-terminated strings, making it easier for shell utilities to consume the spaces in the filenames.  Therefore the following command will get the files I need:</p>

<p><div>
  <pre><code class='bash'>&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;find ~/.cxgames/Steam/drive_c/Program Files/Steam/steamapps/ -name &quot;*.cfg&quot; -print0 | xargs -0 tar -rf ~/etc/steam-settings.tar
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</code></pre>
</div>
</p>

<p>Restoring is as simple as running the following command from within my home directory.</p>

<p><div>
  <pre><code class='bash'>&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;tar xvf ~/etc/steam-settings.tar
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</code></pre>
</div>
</p>

<p>Perhaps some day we&rsquo;ll have a Linux steam client, and a promotional TF2 item named the <strong>Unix Pipe</strong>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2 Cent Tip - Extend (Resize) a Whole Device Partition.]]></title>
    <link href="http://atomic-penguin.github.com/blog/2010/09/02/2-cent-tip-extend-resize-a-whole-device-partition/"/>
    <updated>2010-09-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://atomic-penguin.github.com/blog/2010/09/02/2-cent-tip-extend-resize-a-whole-device-partition</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Occasionally I have to resize partitions on iSCSI or Fiber-Channel attached SAN storage.  Both technologies allow you to easily extend the available storage for a host by extending LUNs, or volumes.  A common problem after extending the size of the LUN, or volume, is resizing partitions to fill out the new size.</p>

<p>For the most part, I usually fire up <a href="http://partedmagic.com">PartedMagic</a> and its a snap, even with Fiber-Channel attached enterprise storage.  Once the HBAs (Host Bus Adapters) have been zoned to Fiber-Channel switches, then the HBAs do all the heavy lifting.  In other words on Fiber-Channel, it doesn&rsquo;t matter if you&rsquo;re using PartedMagic, or <a href="http://www.knopper.net">Knoppix</a>, the server just knows where the storage is and whether it is in an attached state.  The only dependency for this working on a Live boot disk are drivers for the HBA cards.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>iSCSI is a bit different.  Because, iSCSI relies on commodity Network Interface Cards, this technology is largely implemented in software.  One perceived advantage is iSCSI may seem less complicated to use than Fiber-Channel storage.  Unfortunately, in this case, PartedMagic did not have open-iscsi software, and I could install open-iscsi in the Knoppix Live ramdisk. However, because Knoppix came with an outdated iSCSI kernel module, it was not new enough to inter-operate with the open-iscsi software.</p>

<p>Furthermore, the version of <a href="http://www.gnu.org/software/parted/index.shtml">parted</a> that shipped with RHEL 5 threw an incompatible filesystem error, refusing to modify the filesystem. So, in the end, I twiddled some bits on the partition table with fdisk, and used resize2fs to extend the partition.</p>

<p>Assuming you have a backup of the filesystem you are working on, you can proceed with the following steps to extend a single partition to the end of the extended volume.  If you have multiple partitions on a volume, you may want to stick to more reliable methods of resizing and extending.  If you screw up the cylinder boundaries on a device with multiple partitions, you&rsquo;ll definitely lose data.  A single partition, in this example, is a much simpler scenario.</p>

<p>The device name in this example is <code>/dev/mapper/u02</code>, the first partition is <code>/dev/mapper/u02p1</code>:</p>

<p>Run <code>fdisk -l /dev/mapper/u02</code> to get the starting cylinder.</p>

<p><div>
  <pre><code class='bash'>&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;root@localhost:~# fdisk -l /dev/mapper/u02
Disk /dev/mapper/u02: 100.9 GB, 108340550042 bytes

255 heads, 63 sectors/track, 13171 cylinders
Units = cylinders of 16065 * 512 = 8225280 bytes

          Device Boot      Start         End      Blocks   Id  System
/dev/mapper/u02p1               1       13171   26450329   83  Linux
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</code></pre>
</div>
</p>

<p>Reboot the server after extending the volume or LUN on your SAN.  You want to do this before extending the partition in your Operating System.  The Operating System needs to re-read sector 0 on the extended SAN volume, before continuing. Note, that fdisk will report <strong>26109</strong> cylinders instead of <strong>13171</strong>, after rebooting the server.</p>

<p>Next, we will run: <code>fdisk /dev/mapper/u02</code>, and then hit the keys: <code>d, n, p, 1, [enter], [enter], w</code></p>

<p><div>
  <pre><code class='bash'>&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;root@localhost:~# fdisk /dev/mapper/u02
WARNING: DOS-compatible mode is deprecated. It&#39;s strongly recommended to
         switch off the mode (command &#39;c&#39;) and change display units to
         sectors (command &#39;u&#39;).

Command (m for help): d
Selected partition 1

Command (m for help): n
Command action
   e   extended
   p   primary partition (1-4)
p
Partition number (1-4): 1
First cylinder (1-26109, default 1):
Using default value 1
Last cylinder, +cylinders or +size{K,M,G} (1-26109, default 26109):
Using default value 26109

Command (m for help): w
The partition table has been altered!

Calling ioctl() to re-read partition table.
Syncing disks.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</code></pre>
</div>
</p>

<p>Finally, run <code>resize2fs</code> on <code>/dev/mapper/u02p1</code>. If you are using ext3, you can do an on-line resize while the volume is mounted.  It is probably safest to <code>umount</code> the partition to be re-sized, however.</p>

<p><div>
  <pre><code class='bash'>&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;root@localhost:~# resize2fs /dev/mapper/u02p1
resize2fs 1.39 (29-May-2006)
Filesystem at /dev/mapper/u02p1 is mounted on /u02; on-line resizing required
Performing an on-line resize of /dev/mapper/u02p1 to 52430127 (4k) blocks.
The filesystem on /dev/mapper/u02p1 is now 52430127 blocks long.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</code></pre>
</div>
</p>

<p>Refer to the <code>resize2fs</code> for more information on the command, and its proper usage.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2 Cent Tip - Dynamic Rdesktop Resolution.]]></title>
    <link href="http://atomic-penguin.github.com/blog/2010/06/28/2-cent-tip-dynamic-rdesktop-resolution/"/>
    <updated>2010-06-28T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://atomic-penguin.github.com/blog/2010/06/28/2-cent-tip-dynamic-rdesktop-resolution</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So occasionally I do have to touch a Windows system, or use a Windows-only management tool (I&rsquo;m looking at you VMware).  Not that I have any problem with Microsoft or Windows, I&rsquo;m really just more comfortable in a Unix-like environment.  I do use the Open Source <code>rdesktop</code> utility to access Windows machine using version 5.0 of the Remote Desktop Protocol (RDP).</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a handy utility, but I really wish it would give me an appropriate resolution based on the current resolution of my laptop&rsquo;s X Windows session.  There is, in fact, a command line flag to alter the geometry of the remote desktop window.  However, typing in <code>rdesktop -g 1280x1024</code> is much more tedious than typing in <code>rdesktop</code> on the command line interface.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>So the simple solution is to put an alias in the <code>.bashrc</code> file, like so&hellip;</p>

<p><div>
  <pre><code class='bash'>&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# ~/.bashrc
rdesktop=&#39;rdesktop -g 1280x1024&#39;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</code></pre>
</div>
</p>

<p>However, on my laptop, the max resolution without an external monitor is 1600x900.  So I still have to override the setting with <code>rdesktop -g 1280x1024</code> on the command line, any time I am running without an external monitor.</p>

<p>Another solution would be to use <code>awk</code> to find a smaller resolution from <code>xrandr</code>, then set that resolution in my <code>rdesktop</code> alias.</p>

<p><div>
  <pre><code class='bash'>&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# ~/.bashrc
RDESKTOP_SIZE=`xrandr | awk &#39;{getline; getline; getline; print $1; exit;}&#39;`

alias rdesktop=&#39;rdesktop -g $RDESKTOP_SIZE&#39;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</code></pre>
</div>
</p>

<p>This <code>awk</code> command will skip the first three lines, from the xrandr output.  That is two header lines, and the maximum resolution on the following line, which we&rsquo;ll skip.  I&rsquo;ll take the next highest resolution and set that in the variable <code>$RDESKTOP_SIZE</code>.  Finally, I&rsquo;ll use the variable <code>$RDESKTOP_SIZE</code> with the <code>-g</code> switch in <code>rdesktop</code> to properly set my alias.</p>

<p>Let us say you have two big monitors plugged into a port replicator.  Perhaps you only want the <code>rdesktop</code> window to cover part of one screen.  The following code will keep my <code>rdesktop</code> window smaller than one of the 1920x1200 screens on a spanned 3840x1200 resolution.</p>

<p><div>
  <pre><code class='bash'>&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# ~/.bashrc
RDESKTOP_SIZE=`xrandr | awk &#39;{getline; getline; getline; print $1; exit;}&#39;`

if [ $RDESKTOP_SIZE == &quot;3840x1200&quot; ]; then
    RDESKTOP_SIZE=&quot;1820x1100&quot;
fi

alias rdesktop=&#39;rdesktop -g $RDESKTOP_SIZE&#39;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;</code></pre>
</div>
</p>

<p>In other words, if I have two monitors at 1920x1200 each, their combined resolution is reported by <code>xrandr</code> as 3840x1200.  I want to override the detected resolution to 100 pixels less than the resolution on one screen.  Therefore I set the <code>$RDESKTOP_SIZE</code> variable to 1820x1100, before setting my <code>rdesktop</code> alias in <code>.bashrc</code>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
